All right. So today
what I want to
talk about is
containers in general
and then Docker
in particular.
And so what do we
mean by containers?
First of all, I
guess one question I
do want to ask is
how many of you have
worked with Docker
containers before?
If you raise your hands.
A few of you.
How many of you
have built your
own containers?
How many of you
have written
your own Docker files?
docker compose files a
few of you done docker
compose okay so a few
of you this is going
to be old hat if you've
done docker compose
and docker build files
you understand how
that works especially
docker compose and all
the nuances of those
you know this is going
to be definitely review
material your teams
are going to well
actually this is not the
docker assignment i'm
going to give is not
a team assignment so
your teams can help
you with understanding
but they're not going
to be able to help you
with that. You're all
going to be doing your
own version of this
assignment.
So what are containers?
So container, and
we've already talked
about virtual machines.
Virtual machines, I
said, we're emulating
or virtualizing an
entire machine, okay?
We said that we define
things like what's,
how much disk does
it have? How much,
how many CPUs is it
going have in it,
how much memory.
Once we've got the
machine defined, then
what we do is we go
and install an
operating system on it.
It's still virtualized,
but it's a real
operating system
that we run. There's
real storage that the
virtual machine is
using. That operating
system gets installed
on that, and when
we run the virtual
machine, it loads
that operating system.
That operating system
oftentimes can be a
completely different
operating system than
what our host machine
is running the
machine that's actually
running our hypervisor
that gives us the
virtual machine is
probably running its
own operating system
unless you're running
a type one hypervisor
and so these type two
hypervisors usually
are running completely
different os sometimes
you can run the exact
same os but usually
you're oftentimes
running a different
one so for instance
on my mac i'm running
mac os but when i
typically run vms they're
usually linux vms
and they're running a
Linux operating system,
which is completely
different than the
Mac operating system.
Now, when we talked
about the virtual
machines, we said,
OK, these are all the
resources that have to
be given to it. And even
though they're
virtualized, one of the
things I talked about
with memory, for
instance, I said that
if you're going to run,
when you run your
virtual machines, you can
specify how much
memory that you want to
give to that virtual
machine. But but
you're still going to
be limited typically to
the amount of physical
memory that you have
in the host system
that you're running.
And typically,
you're going to
give it a lot
less memory than
what you have on
the host system.
Same thing with
disk resources and
such. You have to
have enough space
for the disk
image for your VM.
A typical disk for
launching a machine
these days is about
the minimum that
you'd want is a
20 gigabyte drive.
Anything smaller and
you're starting to
get real tight,
especially if you want to
load up a bunch of
tools and things like
that. If you've got
very simple stuff, it's
not. The point of all
this is there's a lot
of resources
dedicated to a virtual
machine because we're
virtualizing an entire
machine. okay containers
are try to address
this issue of how
much resources are
available or needed to
run a virtual machine
another example of
how much resources are
required when you
launched your virtual
machines it would
take anywhere from 30
seconds some of you may
have taken upwards of
three minutes to get
a virtual machine
running on your on your
system okay that's a
long time to get
something up and going,
right? You're
essentially running a
program, and it takes
three minutes for
the program to be
ready, right? That's
a long time for a lot
of work that we're
doing, especially
when I'm doing
software engineering
and testing and such.
So containers are
sort of trying to
address this as a
midway point. They're
basically saying, well,
what if we don't start
an entire machine up,
virtualized or not?
Instead of starting an
entire machine, what do
we really need to do
well what we really want
to do is have a process
process of execution
on some system but we
wanted that process
to think that it's
running on a different
machine okay and this
is essentially what
containers do they um
provide an environment for
your pro for your program
to run but they're
wrapping it with
virtualization as if you
were running on a on a
different machine but
the way it's achieving
this is essentially
just giving you a new
file system. How do you
know which machine
that you're running on,
right? You
connect to a name.
If you SSH to a machine,
you got to name a
machine. But once
you got the shell,
how do you know what
machine that you're
on? How can you
verify that? Well,
we're going to do
something and look
at the file system.
Well, if I change
what your file system
looks like underneath
you, I can give
you the impression
that you're running
on a completely
different system, right?
And so this is
the basis of what
containers are doing.
They're basically
saying, we don't
have to set up a
whole new, virtualize
a whole machine.
All we have to do
is get a process
running and virtualize
essentially the file
system that it's
running under, okay?
And we can give it a
different file system.
Now, Docker is what
we're going to look
at in particular as
a technology that
does this, But
containers are around
for lots of different
environments
and lots of different
– well, basically,
there's lots of
different containers
out there and
container environments.
You can do container
environments that
are more generalized
like Docker, which
generalizes
essentially the entire
operating system,
especially in terms of
Linux-type operating
systems and such.
Or you can have
containers that have
been around for
a while that are
more specialized.
So, for instance,
Java has a popular
container architecture
called Tomcat. And
what it's for is
to be able to drop
your Java applications
into a Tomcat
environment. And the
Tomcat will provide
all the resources
or virtualize all
those resources around
that your application
wants to use.
So there's lots
of different
container technologies.
Docker is one
that's been widely
adopted, has taken
off, and one that we're
going to go ahead
and study as a
particular implementation
of containers.
And so a lot of
the examples we're
going to be talking
about are containers.
So they virtualize
the operating
system itself.
Remember, with a virtual
machine, we virtualize
the machine,
and put a real
operating system
in it, in the
virtual machine.
Here, we're virtualizing,
essentially
thinking of it as
virtualizing the
operating system.
Now, when we do this,
we are going to see
some limitations
of this. We'll talk
about the limitations
of containers in just
a second. But they
have some incredible
advantages to them.
The first biggest
advantage of containers
is they are usually,
especially containers
like Docker systems
or the Docker
system for building
containers, they're
incredibly lightweight.
Okay, what do we
mean by lightweight?
Well, lightweight
means usually the
amount of resources
to install a
container are pretty
small comparatively.
said, if I'm going
to start up a virtual
machine, I'm probably
going to have at least a
gigabyte or two worth
of file system space
for my virtual machine
disk image, probably
even larger than that.
In other words, if you
have a real machine
that comes up or a
virtual machine that comes
up and it's got tools
that you want to use
and everything, it
can easily be 20 gigabytes
worth of storage to
be able to do that
with a container often
containers the size size
of those are measured
in megabytes not
gigabytes um hundreds of
giga megabytes for
large containers many
containers are much much
smaller than that um
so in terms of size
much smaller in terms of
memory resources
we're going to see the
containers are essentially
taking up as much
memory as a single process
would take up. They
don't have to reserve
two, three, four
gigabytes worth of
memory to be able to do
something interesting. A
lot of virtual machines
may only do a gigabyte,
but they're still
using up a whole gigabyte.
Typically, a process
is going to use far,
far less than that,
okay?
Another big area
where we can
see this in terms
of lightweight
is how fast
containers come up.
If I launch a VM,
I said earlier,
30 seconds to maybe
three minutes,
right?
With containers,
it's not unusual for
them to come up
in under a second.
So you can have,
you get to the
command and you'll
get the process
running in under
a second, right?
So there are
a lot of ways
that they are
lightweight.
Now, when you
run a container,
and this is an
important thing,
when you run a container,
it is a single process
running under
the host OS.
Okay, it's one process.
We're doing some
special things with that
process, and we're going
to talk a little bit
more about those,
but it's one process
that's running when you
launch a container. We
talk about containers
talking to each other
and attaching to
containers and things like
that. What we're still
talking about is one
process that's running
under the host OS.
When we talk about
virtual machines,
yeah, there's a
process, which is the
hypervisor that starts
the virtual machine, but
typically that may
have several processes
in and of itself.
And then inside that
virtual machine, it's
virtualizing other
processes as well. So
when you have a virtual
machine, you can
log into it and get
multiple process threads
and you can see them.
We can log into a
virtual machine and run
the PS command, for
instance, if we're
running a Linux OS in
our virtual machine and
see all the processes
running on that
virtual machine. We can
interact with those,
right? We are interacting
with the kernel of
the operating system
on a virtual machine.
So whatever capabilities
that particular
kernel has on that
operating system on that
virtual machine, our
process will have access to
or a program can have
access to. We can
learn multiple threads
and all kinds of stuff.
When you're talking
about containers,
especially Docker
containers,
they're running
one process.
They don't have
multiple processes.
We'll show how we
can sort of get
another process
attached to a container.
It's not technically
attached.
But we can give you
the – I'll show you how
you can get the feel
that you've got another
process running. But
if you ran the ps
command inside your
container, you're not going
to get a list of
processes back because
there aren't a whole
bunch of processes. There
will only show up
one because it's not
running. Now, and the
other thing about this
is that it's using,
as I said, the host OS
is one hosting that is
running that process,
which means that
whenever your container
process wants to
access a kernel call, a
system call, it's accessing
the system, the host
system. Now, there's
some brokerage going
on with the – there is
a daemon that starts
up your Docker container,
and it sets some
limitations on that
process when it runs.
So there are some
things preventing that,
but it's a very
different environment
from a process perspective,
right? When you
look at what's going
on inside a container,
you don't see
what looks like an
operating system. You
got the commands, you
can do LS and lots of
other commands, you
can do network commands
and other things,
but when you take
a look at what the
whole environment is
that you're running in,
it doesn't look like
an operating system,
because it's not an
operating system.
Essentially, you're
running a single
process with a version
of a file system
that that container
wants that process
to see that's
different than the OS.
um and what we do is
uh now the container
has its own version of
what the file system
is we're going to
talk about that in a
little bit but you
can map host os file
systems into that
containers file system as
well so there's a
way for us to sort of
merge these two inside
a container now this
also uh gives us some
nice advantages and
when we're working
with virtual machines
So some people had
some problems because
Vagrant wasn't behaving
like it used to.
When working with
the virtual machines,
we didn't really
have a way for
your virtual machine
and your host to
communicate easily
between each other.
Vagrant would set up
this slash Vagrant
directory that would
be mapped to it.
But actually, if you
take a look at what
it's doing underneath
the covers, it's
literally just
running a file sharing
protocol on the virtual
machine and having
that file sharing
protocol attached via
the internal network
to your host OS.
So these OSs are
not intimately
connected together
in any kind of ways.
We're just using
standard network file
sharing to give
you a directory on
your VM that mapped
into your host OS,
okay?
When we're doing running
containers, the file
system that the
container sees is sitting
in the host OS, and
we can easily attach
other directories and
such from the host OS to
that version of the file
system. It's a much,
much more integrated
way of doing things
that has advantages and
disadvantages to it.
And the biggest thing
is whenever we are
doing a system call
or want to call to
the resources of the
kernel to do anything,
it's going to be
the host OS's kernel
that's responding to
it. It's not going
to be a different
operating system running
in a virtual machine
that's doing it.
which means I can't run.
When I run a container,
the process
has to be able
to run on my
host OS already.
In other words, I
should be able to
take that process
and maybe have to get
additional libraries
or other kinds
of dependencies
resolved on my host OS,
but the process
inside the container
needs to be able to
run on the host OS,
provided it's got
all those additional
resources available
to it in the host OS.
That's not the same thing
with a virtual machine.
Remember, a virtual
machine, I can
launch a completely
different OS.
So I can be on
my Mac, launch
a virtual machine
for Windows,
and run programs that are
compiled and
built for Windows.
Right?
If I run a container,
processes I run in
that container would
have to be able to
run on my Mac as well.
Right? Because it's
using the host OS's
system. Does this
make sense, everyone?
These are some of
the fundamental
limitations. So
that means typically
when we're running
a container,
especially Docker
containers, these are
Linux environments
that they're running,
we're running under
a Linux system.
Now, we have a
product called Docker
for Windows and
Docker for Mac. When
you install these,
what they literally
do is they create
a small virtual
machine, a small
virtual Linux machine.
So even though you're
running Windows,
it brings up a small
Linux virtual machine
and runs your Docker
containers in that. It
uses the Linux OS of the
small virtual machine
and then says, okay,
I'm going to run a
process in there as a
container inside that.
That's the way Docker
for Windows works.
It's the same way that
Docker for Mac works.
If you install
Docker on a Linux
system, though, it
doesn't have to run
a little tiny virtual
machine. It can
use the underlying
Linux OS directly.
Does this make
sense to everyone?
So this is one of
the big differences
between containers
and virtual
machines. They're
not the same thing.
At a casual glance,
they can look the
same, and at a
casual and a very
superficial kind of
comparison between
virtual machines and
containers, one could
say, well, they
do the same thing.
They function in many
of the same respects,
but they do have
these limitations that
we have to understand
about what a container
can or can't do and
what it is and what
it isn't compared to
a virtual machine.
However, these
lightweight notions
that it's really
quick and easy to get
these things up
and running, and
they're still very
portable, is helpful.
So let's talk about
Docker in particular.
Docker's been around
for a while. Well,
Docker is based
on the Linux OS.
It depends on a
couple features in
the Linux kernel
in particular.
One of those is
a capability in
the Linux kernel
called Cgroups.
Cgroups allows a
process or a root
process to be able
to coordinate another
process or a group
of process and be
able to limit things
like CPU, memory,
and other kinds of
resources to those
processes in what's
called a C group.
So one of the things
that – the way that
Docker works is it has
– I mentioned, made
reference that it
has its own Docker
daemon that coordinates
the launching of
the containers and
shutting containers down.
It's basically starting
these processes
that I was talking
about. A container is
a process. So it's
the one responsible
for starting that
process and everything.
and it starts those
under C groups so that
it can have that
control or prescribed
parameters that the
kernel is going to
enforce for the Docker
daemon on how that
container is going
to work in terms of
limitations and things
like that. The other
thing that they
rely on for Linux is
Linux has this command
called change root.
Change root is kind
of an interesting
command. Again, it's
only available to root
access that you have to
be a system administrator
on your Linux system
to use this. But
change root allows
you to start a process
and change its perception
of the file system.
Change root, the
reason why we
call it change
root is because
normally when you
launch a process,
you see the root of
the OS's file system as
the root of your file
system. And so you can
start at the OS and
go down to slash USR,
slash bin, for instance,
to find commands.
You can go slash home,
slash cipher, for
instance, on my system
to find my account and
so forth, right? When
you use change root
to launch a process,
what you're doing is
telling the process,
no, no, don't use the
slash at the top of
the real file system.
Use some other
directory inside the
file system and
treat that as root.
Now, it's the kernel
that does this. So
change root is a command
that has to be done
by the super user.
The Docker daemon runs
as the super user
when you start it up.
And so it has access
to this change root
capability. And so
when it launches the
container processes,
it literally changes
what they see as their
root when they're
launching. And this
is a critical thing.
Okay.
Does this make
sense to everyone?
Right?
So change root is kind
of a cool thing. You
can use it for
doing some – system
administrators have been
using it for years to
do certain things,
like when you would log
into a system, say, as
anonymous or something
like that, or some
kind of process that
was allowing to log
into a system, they
would often change
route that process so
that if you logged
in, you would get the
route that was
defined by the system
administrator, which would
often be a directory.
and it would
often be very
limited in terms
of what it has
but Docker takes
advantage of it to
use this as I mentioned
before there's
versions for
Windows and Mac OS
when you install
and run these
I'll demonstrate
the Mac OS
version here in
just a second
like I said they
go ahead and
create their own
small little Linux
VM for running
the containers
and then and the
Docker daemon running
in Windows or Mac
OS then controls all
the container
processes that are run.
Excuse me.
So Docker installs as
a daemon process on
your OS. So if you
install it under Mac OS
or Windows OS, it's
going to have to have
root authority to
execute your programs.
If you install it in
Linux environment, And
you need to install
it to launch as root.
So it's typically
installed as a, well,
it's a daemon process.
So we typically
set it up to the
daemon process to
launch when we start
our Linux system.
And then, as I
mentioned before, the
daemon starts a
subprocess for each
container that
you ask it to run.
So we'll take a look
at some containers
in just a second. So
how do we get containers
though? Well, containers
come from what
we call container
images or Docker anyways
does this. And what
a container image
is, is essentially
the container image is
a, well, first of
all, it is a combined
file object. It's one
file for the container
image, but it's got
multiple components
in it. And one of
those components is a
file that represents
the file system that
you want your container
process to see.
It's the version
of the file
system that you
want it to see.
Okay?
And it can be
as limited or
expansive as you
want it to be.
But you're going
to copy all the
files that you want
your container to
be able to see into
this image file.
Okay?
And we do it in a
particular way and
such. And, shoot,
sorry about that.
I keep forgetting
to upgrade
my firewall
and my laptop.
Where was I?
Docker files. Oh,
yeah. So it builds up
this image file,
and then some other
associated information
goes into the image.
And that's what the
Docker daemon needs to
have access to. It
says, okay, I need to
know which image,
when you go to run a
container, you have to
tell it which image or
Docker container image
that you want to use.
So when we talk
about a container,
typically when we talk
about a container, what
we actually mean is
a running instance
of a particular
container image, okay?
We use the term a little
bit interchangeably,
so sometimes we
mean a little
bit more generically
as the image itself,
But oftentimes
when we refer to a
container, we're
referring to it as a
particular running
instance of a container.
So how do we build
these images?
Well, we have a
command called Docker
build that will
build images for us.
But it needs a set
of instructions on
how to build that
image. And that is
called a Docker
file. So when you run
Docker build, you
specify the location of
a Docker file that
contains all the
instructions for how
to build that image.
Now, when you take a
look at it, I'll take
a look at the Docker
file in just a second
here. When you have a
Docker file, there's
a series of commands
to it. And each
one of those commands,
more or less, is
essentially going to
build a layer. One of
the things about Docker
images is that they're
what they call a
unified file system.
They build their file
system image in layers.
So you'll copy some
files onto that
image, and that forms
a layer. And then
if you do some more
changes to files
on an image, that's
another layer.
And then there can
be a third layer, a
fourth layer, a
fifth layer, and you
can have as many
layers as you want to.
The reason why they
do this is there are
a bunch of layers,
but it's sort of like
when you're working with
graphic design tools
and such. They will
typically allow you
to create layers of
images, and then they
show you the view
as all those images
smash together so that
you can see the one
on top of each other.
This is essentially
what happens with our
file system layers
when we're building
a Docker file. We lay
one down, we lay another
one, And the image
that we eventually
see is the combination
of all those layers
smashed together, the
results of all those
when they're done.
The reason why we
do this, though, and
I'll demonstrate
this to you in a
little bit, is it
saves a bunch of time.
If we make a
change to our
Docker file, we
want to make a
change to how
that image works.
If we're building up
each layer, the other
neat thing about the
way they do that is
it can detect which
layers it needs to
rebuild for the changes
that you made in
the Docker file. So
if it doesn't have to
rebuild certain layers
because you didn't
make any changes that
would affect them,
Docker automatically
picks it up and speeds
up the build process
so that our image
doesn't take nearly
as long to build if
we're making small
changes as opposed to
the very first time
we build our image.
And so that's what
this Dockerfile does.
And then finally,
we do some setups on
the Dockerfile. Usually,
you have a Dockerfile
that builds up the
image in terms of
some various directives.
And then there's
some directives
usually about running
the program that you
want in that process.
So the other thing
about the Dockerfiles,
they not only build the
image, they build up
the environment that
your process is going to
run. So you can set
up initial environment
variables that you
want access to. You can
set up some other
capabilities or information
for the process that
runs inside the container
when it launches
that container image.
When you're building
container images,
typically we don't build
them from scratch. We
usually will start with
a base image. um and
there's lots of base
images uh available we'll
talk about where you
get these base images
in a second um from
the docker hub um but
um you build them up
uh so there's a lot so
you typically will use
a base image now um
the images we're going
to use to demonstrate
some things in here
are going to be Ubuntu
images, okay? Very
similar to Ubuntu's with
the OS that's running
on Silo. So when we use
these images and pull
them in, we'll end up
getting with a base
image that looks very
similar to Silo. You'll
be able to see all
the same command, many
of the same commands
that you would use, you
could use on Silo, or
a typical Linux installation
will be available
inside of our containers
automatically.
If we go into our
container, we have a
shell in our container
we can go see and
walk that file system
and see all the
utilities and such that
would match up to what
we would see in silo
however if you're
building a generic
um ubuntu base image
say ubuntu 22 as their
as your base image
that base image does
not have things like
developer tools in
it similar to when we
launched our vms we
used ubuntu as our um um
image that we were using
for our VM, it didn't
have compilers and
other compilation
tools installed, so we
had to do an APT install
to get those tools
into our VM's image,
or into our VM's
OS, and then we
could do things
like build Angband.
We could build Angband
inside a container,
but if our base image
doesn't have all
those tools, then
the image that we're
going to use to build
Angband has to include
all those tools,
okay? So we have to
put those into those
layers. So we'll do a
base of Ubuntu, and
then immediately after
that, we'll do an
install of all these
development tools
on that base image.
And then we could
add additional
stuff like another
layer for our
repository and things
of that nature.
now um when we are um
so we build these up
off of base images now
ubuntu is a big base
image though and it's
actually we don't
typically build a lot
of containers that are
built for deployment
testing development
purposes and especially
in production
environments we don't
typically use something like
ubuntu as our base
image because it's got
a whole bunch of stuff
that probably isn't
actually going to be
used by our process.
For instance, I could
install an OnBond onto
a Ubuntu base image,
but an OnBond is
never going to take
advantage of LS or move
or dozens of other
commands and libraries
that are available in
the base Ubuntu image.
That's just wasted
space for my OnBond
deployment. If all I
want to do is deploy,
give you a container
that allows you to
say, here, take this,
you can run OnBond
and that's all you
got to do. You don't
have to install
it. you don't have
to compile it or
anything, just take this
container and run
it, which I'm going
to show you in a
second, we can do.
We probably wouldn't
want to base it
off of Ubuntu because
Ubuntu, like I
said, has a whole
bunch of extra stuff
that we don't need.
We definitely wouldn't
want to give you
a container image
that we had built
Ubuntu or Angband in.
Because if we built
Angband in that
container image, that
means we got to have a
GCC compiler and all
the build tools in
there as well. The
only time we ever need
those are when we're
building Anban. We
don't need it to run
it. So why would I
hand all that stuff
to you just to run it?
So typically, when
we're building
containers,
especially for
deployment purposes
and such, we wouldn't
use Ubuntu as
our base image.
We would use, there's
these very tiny,
bare bones Linux images
that we can use as
a base. Alpine is a
typical one. It has
the minimal amount
of library tools that
you would expect for
a Linux environment.
And it's very,
very small, less
than, I think
it's around 20
megabytes or
something like that.
Now, if you use that
as a base image, it's
great in terms of size
and everything. But
it's got a problem,
which is it doesn't have
all the tools that
you expect. So if you
try to run a shell,
first of all, you might
not even be able to
run a shell inside your
container. You might
be able to run your
OnBond, but nothing else
inside the container,
okay?
And if you do have a
shell, you might not
have, like, the move
command or other commands
that you would expect
to find, right? You
have to install those.
So we have to run this
sort of game of
figuring out, okay, how
much do we actually
need to be able to, A,
run our process, and,
B, actually figure out
that our process is
running correctly in there
versus a full Ubuntu
environment, right?
So this is one of
the first questions
we always make
is, which base
environment do we
want to build from?
We can then use the
Dockerfile directives
to install additional
things. The other
thing I'm going to
point out is that we
can actually build
a couple images. We
can have what we call
multi-stage builds.
So we can build an
image with a whole bunch
of stuff, stuff that
we need, and then
build another image
that we can copy things
from that other one.
So we're going to build
an image that we, say,
do compile on BondIn
with all of our tools
and such, and then
build another image
and just copy into that
second image everything
that we need. And
that second image is
the one that's actually
then given away as
part of the container.
We'll talk about that
probably on
Monday, though.
Environment
variables, user
settings, port mappings.
One of the beautiful
things about containers,
this is a hallmark,
one of the other
hallmarks of containers.
When you're building a
container, the rule of
thumb about building
containers is that you
build a container to
do one thing and one
thing very, very well,
and just the one thing.
And then if your
application needs
other things that
need to go on, don't
pile them into the
same container.
Start up other
containers and have
the containers
talk to each other.
This is a typical
way that we do
things, but they're
going to talk to
each other over
networking protocols.
So one of the things
we have to do is know
something about how
those networking
protocols work, hence
the reason why we're
talking about data
networks for a while.
And when we talk about
port mappings, you'll
understand, oh,
ports, those are the
things that say which
application something
goes to. And so
hopefully this will start
to have a little bit
more meaning to you
when we talk about how
port mappings work.
We'll talk about that
in a second because
we have to understand
what a port means
inside the container's
perspective versus a
port looking from
outside the container.
And then also we
have a similar thing,
as I mentioned
already. We can take
local file systems
on the host OS and
expose those and
sort of blend those
into the container's
image of the file
system so we can
get this mixed view.
What's nice about that
is your container has
a fixed image that your
process knows about,
And then you can
expose portions of your
host OS's file system
to the container for
things like runtime
configuration information
or runtime kinds of
things. In other words,
here's a container that
generally will work
on some kind of set
of files or something,
but I want it to work
on my set of files, not
the ones inside the
container. So I can run
the container to work
on a set of files and
then map a directory
from my host OS that
contains the files I
want the container to
work on. So we'll show
some examples of that.
We can attach to
containment. So there
is a – and Docker
does have a term for
it or a command
called docker attach.
But that's not
probably going to do
what you think it
does with a container.
When you do a docker
attach, what the
default behavior
essentially for that
is to basically say,
okay, you've got
this process running,
and I want to
attach to the process.
It really doesn't
mean you can get
into the process.
Typically, what it
just means from the
container's perspective
is you can get
output from the
process. So the default
behavior, if you
do a Docker attach,
is to basically
essentially plug
in the standard out
from the process
that you're running
to the terminal
session that you
are attaching.
And it just basically
gives you the output
of your program. That's
probably not what you
want. Typically, when
we think about attaching
to a container,
people are thinking,
oh, I got this container
running. I've got
Anban running, but I
want to see what's going
on inside the container,
right? Now, here's
the first issue with
that kind of thinking.
There's nothing
going on inside
the container except
the one process
that's running,
Anban, okay?
What you really
are asking, though,
typically when
people are wanting to
do this, is they
want to see what the
file system is that
Anban is seeing.
And the way that
Docker provides us a
mechanism to do that or
similar kinds of things,
we can affect the
file system that our
container is working
on by doing a Docker
exec and specifying
the running container
and then specifying
a command in the
container's file system
that we want to run.
So if we built our
container with a shell
program inside the
container's file system,
we can then, once we
have the container
up and running,
an instance of it
running on that image,
we can run another
process and give it
access to see the
same image as the
container, the container
that's running.
Everyone get this?
The difference is it's
not running, the second
process is not running
in the container.
All it's doing is
running its own
process, a shell
program, that has
the same visibility
of the file
system that the
container is using.
It's been change
-rooted just like the
original program
in our container.
So now the shell
gives you a view of
what's in there,
but don't mistake it
for a process running
in the container.
If you had to
still go back
to the original container
and do a PS command,
you wouldn't see the
second process running
inside your container.
You'd still only
see the one process.
The other one's
a completely
separate process
in your host OS.
It's just been
change-rooted to
use the same file
system image that
your container
is already using.
Does this make
sense, everyone?
I'll demonstrate all this
stuff in just a second.
and then containers
work together now we
use um docker file
to build a container
image and i said
containers um should do
one thing really
well and if you have
multiple things that
need to be done well
um then you run
multiple containers a
great example is
typically brought out is
let's say that you're
designing a web
application oftentimes
we might use react
is our front-end,
which runs on Node.js.
We often would
then use maybe some
kind of back-end
API. You could
use Python,
something like that,
say implement that in
a flask to framework
to be able to get a
simple web service API.
And then you
have a database,
right?
Usually you're going
to have a database
to keep your data
for your application.
Those are three
different components.
In a more traditional
way of doing
things, you might
run each of those
three components,
or even a more
primitive way
would have been to
implement each of
those three yourself,
or just run those three
components on one system.
We still want to have
all those components
as part of our
application, but we don't
want to have to have a
mechanism where we're
trying to build all
three of those ourselves
so that we can get
everything going. So
the typical way that
you would do this under
Docker is you would
make a Docker container
for your front-end,
and it does Node.js.
You do a Docker
container for your API,
web API,
as I'm suggesting written
in Flask or something,
that runs under
another container.
And then your
database would be
running in a
third container.
Each container would
be specialized to
do exactly what it
needs to do. And
then what you need
to do is just get
those containers to
talk to each other.
Well, and we
can do that by
mapping ports and
such between these
and be able to
hook them up.
Docker gives us a way
of doing this so that
if we've broken our
application into
multiple containers,
we can create a Docker
Compose file, and it'll
allow us to the Compose
file, just as the
Docker file tells us
how to build an individual
image, the Docker
Compose tells us how
to start up all these
containers that have
this relationship,
right? My theoretical
app has three
containers. It'll
start up all three of
the containers and
make sure they're all
hooked up together
so that they can
communicate correctly
with each other.
That's what the Docker
Compose does for us.
Now, there are other
systems for doing
this. Kubernetes
is probably the
biggest one that
you might have heard
in reference to
Docker or containers.
Kubernetes is Docker
Compose on steroids.
It does an incredible
amount of management
of containers, and
you have incredible
fidelity and preciseness
in how you want your
containers to work,
and it can do all kinds
of really cool automated
things. So, for
instance, if a container
crashes or misbehaves
for some reason or
no longer seems to be
responding or something's
happened to it,
Kubernetes can
automatically kill it and
restart another one
for you automatically.
If your application's
starting to exhibit
load, Kubernetes
can scale your
application up and
add more containers or
scale them down. It
has a whole bunch of
capabilities for
managing containers.
So it's – but
along with all that
capability for management
comes additional
overhead. So if
you're going to –
Kubernetes is a great
tool to learn and
to work with, but
learn basic Docker
first and then move
up to Kubernetes.
Otherwise, you may
end up being a little
bit more confused
than you need to be.
So let's see.
That's basically the
discussion I wanted
to make about
this stuff. So
let's do a couple
simple demonstrations
of that.
um so i've got docker
for mac installed on
here so we can you
can do a lot of stuff
with this it gives you
this dashboard capability
when you launch it
um docker for windows
does a similar kind
of thing over here on
the left hand side we
have a bunch of places
so we have containers
when it says containers
here it's referencing
containers that
are either currently
running or have run okay
it basically means
that we have set up
their their image
environment so i've got three
of these that have
run now typically what
happens with uh dockers
when you start up
a docker container if
you uh first of all
it's got a name these
are randomly generated
names i could specify
a name if you don't
specify a name for
your container when you
launch it when you do
a docker run docker
will automatically
generate a name for you
why because generally
we like to use this
rather than the ids
which look like this the
ids are just hash um
hash ids um and they're
ugly and humans usually
don't like to pay
attention to those
but pensive gates even
though it does it's
nonsense still is more
meaningful than d979
blah blah blah and like
i said i can name them
whatever I want to.
Now, this tells me,
it tells me what
image file it would
use. So these were
using an Ubuntu
base image that I
launched. This one's
using my Cyphered
Angbon. I'd have to
expand that row out.
Since these are
no longer running,
there's no CPU
utilization on these. And
I ran these two four
months ago, the last
class. This one's
one I did just before
class day. And I
could delete these out
or I could restart
these if I wanted to.
We come down
here to images.
Well, this is a
list of the Docker
images that I have
downloaded or built
and are available
to my Docker daemon.
Notice I've got
a lot more images
here than what I
had in containers
primarily because most
of the containers,
when I run them, I
actually will delete them
as soon as I'm done.
I'll throw them away
right away. I don't want
to keep them around.
um volumes i don't
have any volumes in
here but this is a way
that i can define what
we call docker volumes
docker volumes are
areas of your host file
system that are going
to be made available
to your containers
um when you launch
them so you can attach
them and so So you can
think of this as when
I launch a container,
I can have a standard
storage location
that I want any of my
containers to be able
to mount in my host OS.
And so I can define
them as volumes, and
then when a container
is brought up, I
can attach that volume
to that container,
and now it sees the
information inside
there. But it's a
resource that stays with
my OS. It doesn't go
with the container.
It stays with the OS.
That's just when I
bring up the container,
I say, use this
Docker volume on my
host OS for some of
your work or storing
things. And then we
have build processes.
So these are some of
the builds that I've
done and so forth.
Docker Hub.
This is, when you
click on this, what
you're actually going
to is a website.
Now, this is
called what Docker
has the notion of
what's called a
registry. When you
build a Docker image,
that's going to be on
your local machine, okay?
And that's not going
to be very useful
because you want other
people to get your
Docker image. So you
could email them or
share it through a file
system or something
like that. But
typically what we do is
we push our Docker
images to a registry,
okay?
And your registry,
there can be private
registries and
public registries.
By default, if you
don't specify the
registry, you're going
to use the public
registry. And what do
I mean by the public
registry? Well, you
can have multiple
public registries,
but as far as Docker
contains, Docker Hub
is the name of their
public registry. And
if you don't specify
a registry when
you're using Docker,
it's going to assume
that you mean Docker
Hub, and that's where
it's going to go.
You, as an organization,
you can run your
own private registry.
You have Docker
container images that are
for your organization,
but you don't want
them to be out for
anybody to be able to
download or access.
Set up your own
registry in your own
organization and push
your Docker images to your
personal organization's
private registry.
But the public hub
or a Docker hub is a
great place to start
with. In the Docker
Hub, there are official
image releases from
Docker that you can
get. There are official
images for various
developers that
have released their
stuff. So if you want an
Oracle database or
other kinds of services,
you can go find a
Docker image supported
officially by that
developer, and they
place it and maintain
it in Docker Hub.
Likewise, if you
want, and this
is great for open
source tools,
most open source tools
have Docker images
that have been
officially sponsored.
So officially
sponsored open source
tools are things like
GCC and things of
this nature, where
they're open source
tools and they work
with whoever's sort
of the central
management team for
the open-source tool
and release official
open-source versions
of the tools.
And then finally,
anybody can register
on the Docker Hub.
In fact, I'm going
to have you guys
register your own
account on Docker Hub
as part of the
container assignment
I'll give you next
week, or actually
I'll give it to you
after the midterm.
And anybody can push
their own images up.
And you can, once
you push them up to
the public Docker
hub, anybody can grab
your image and pull
them down, right? So,
this is an easy way
to share. If you go
over here, you can
go search on it. So,
obviously, they're
highlighting some things
like LLMs and AI
kinds of things going
on because that's
got a lot of panache
right now. Everyone's
interested in that.
So, this is the
containers. Now, I
don't typically use
the dashboard itself
directly for doing
a lot of things.
You can, but I'm
a little bit old
school, and I
tend to use the
command line tools
for this stuff.
So in my Mac, I've got
a directory for P465.
It's a Docker
directory. I'm going to
demonstrate a couple
things in here. One thing
I want to point out
to you, when you go to
use Docker, you need
to install Docker for
Windows or Docker for
Mac on your laptop.
You cannot use
Silo to run Docker.
We do have a special
machine called Silo
Docker or Burrow Docker,
two names for it,
which you could. You
have to have an account
on there, and I have
to sponsor it. And
I will sponsor it
for somebody. If for
some reason your machine
can't run the Docker
on your laptop, let
me know. And I can
get you a sponsored
account on SiloDocker.
I want to explain a
little bit about this
as well. Remember I
said that Docker has
a daemon process, and
that's what starts
your container process,
right? When you
want to run a container,
I said it's the
Docker daemon that
starts up your process.
Well, the Docker
daemon runs as root,
okay?
And when you run a
Docker container,
it runs as root by
default in your host OS
because the Docker
daemon is running it.
You can tell the Docker
daemon to run under
a different UID than
the root UID, okay?
But by default, it's
running under root.
That means that you
need to, in order for
you to run, to be able
to tell the demon to
do something as root,
you need to have that
root authority
yourself. And we don't
hand out root authority
to silo. Now, there
is a mechanism for
doing what we call sudo
that will allow a non
-privileged user to
have access to privilege
commands selectively.
And so typically you
would use sudo as a
way to set this up.
But because there's
some other risks with
running docker containers
um especially if you
can let if you're
going to let somebody
run any kind of container
that they want to
like we would for
students in silo there
are some additional
risks um associated
with that so rather than
running those on silo
where we would those
risks would be incurred
by every but all
students who are using
it we've moved all
the docker stuff of
silo docker and those
risks are only going
to be pertained for the
students who are explicitly
using that central
service for running
Docker containers.
And also, I want to
come back to this
whole notion of running
as root or running
under a different
UID. This gets a
little bit confusing
with containers, but
I'll explain that
probably on Monday.
So for us, we're
going to run Docker
on our laptops
because we all should
have system or essentially
root authority.
There should be
a problem with us
running Docker
containers. So, let's
run a Docker container
that I've got on
here real quick.
Let's do Docker run.
Docker containers
actually
have a format to them.
Now, the full format
is host name, which
in this case would be
local host, and then
actually, I'm not going
to do it that way.
For instance, we
could do Docker Hub
as the host name,
and then we could
have a port
name, port number
associated with that.
I can't remember
what the port number
is for Docker.
And then we would have
something like this.
So a full specification
for a container
would be include
this host
information. This host
information is the
registry from which
we expect to be
able to grab this
container image.
And basically, if we
don't specify one,
our Docker container
is going to – or Docker
daemon is going to
look at its own list of
container images it's
got and try to pick
one of those. Or it's
going to assume Docker
Hub as the host, the
public registry, and
try to go find the name
of the container that
you gave it out in the
public registry and
grab it and bring it
down. The second part
is what we call – is
called the namespace.
Typically, if you're in
the Docker Hub, that's
going to be your
identity in Docker Hub.
You'll typically use
it as a way to identify
your company or
organization if you're
doing local ones.
And then you have the
name of the image
that you want itself.
And so this is
ciphered namespace.
I've got an on-bond
image. And then
finally, on the
end, we can have one
other field, which
is known as the tag.
Now, a tag is just
a human description
of this particular
version of ciphered
Ongbans. So I could
have several ciphered
Ongbans, each one
with a different tag.
If we don't
specify a tag, it's
assumed to be the
tag of latest.
Latest means
finally the most
current ciphered
on bond there is,
okay? But I could
have others.
So, for instance, I
could have, you know,
I could have one as V1
versus V2 versus V3.
I could have one,
and we'll talk about
building for images or
building for certain
architectures. You
know, you might say
something like x86 versus
an ARM build, right?
And so you can just
put a tag on the end
of that as the way we
refer to this. So I'm
just going to go ahead
and start this as
run Seifert Ongbond.
Now, what's this do?
Well, what it should
do is run Ongbond.
All that container
has is when I run the
container, it has a
directive, builds up a file
system that's appropriate
for Ongbond, and
then launches that
process, and that's what
I get. And I can start
playing Ongbond on
here. Now, I'm running
inside my container.
Why is this? There we go.
This one's got a
little bit of a problem
with the way this
terminal session's set up.
But this is Anbans
running in that
container now.
But let's say that
I wanted to take
a look at what
that container
image looks like.
Remember, I said we
don't want to attach,
because attach does
something slightly
different. But what I did
say was we can go ahead
and exec another process
inside that image.
Now, I need to know
which image I have.
So if I run Docker PS,
this will tell me what
Docker containers
that I've got running.
So Docker PS is a
command to tell me
what images or Docker
containers I've
got running. Here's
the container ID.
Here's the image it
came from. there's
the command it's
actually running I
started 50 seconds ago
still running there's
no ports mapped and
then we have the
name this is the name
that's automatically
generated by the
docker demon angry
raymond so what
I can do now is I
could say well I want
to do a docker exec
minus it this basically
gives me interactive
access to the process
I'm going to run
and then Then I need
to tell it which
container. Now, I mean
by not container image,
but which container
is actually running
that I want to run my
other process in. I
could specify this in
two different ways.
I could either give
it the container ID,
or I can give it the
container name. I'm
going to go with
the container name
because it's a lot
easier for me to type.
So now I've specified
the container. What
I want to do is exec.
So what do I want to
exec? Well, I know this
container image has
bash in the bin
directory. So I'm going
to say bin bash is
what I want to run.
What did I do wrong here?
Did I spell
something wrong here?
Oh, yeah, I did.
There we go.
Now I get a prompt.
It probably looks
a little bit weird,
but this number
right here is the ID
that we saw for the
container. So this
is telling me, if
I type ls in here,
I see on bond, but
notice the directory
it says that I'm
in, slash app,
right?
I can do a cd up, get a
better idea of
what I'm in,
and I take a
look. This is the
image that I'm
seeing. I've cd'd to
the root as far
up as I can, but
this is not my
macOS file system.
This is the image that
was in the container.
it's been essentially
unrolled and the process
started so and sees
this as its root this
is what the on bond
sees running so when
i when i'm running the
on bond process it's
running in here now
if i do a ps there's
nothing here i don't
see on bond running it's
still running over here
even though it's not
working quite right
because of the um
keystroke uh the this
keystroke stuff isn't
working I'm quite right.
I'm not sure what's
going on with that.
It's not recognizing it.
But I don't see
it over here. And
that's because this
is another process
executed under my
host OS. It just
has been change
-rooted to use the same
file system image
as my container.
And so the things
I'm doing in here
look like I'm in
that file system.
And indeed, Angbon
needs those game
files. So where are
those located at?
Well, this, you would
have to know that
I've set this up so
that my game files
are in slash Vagrant
and Angban Live.
And in here, I've
got my game data
files, for
instance. We get in
here, and here's
our favorite monster
.txt file and
things like that.
Point of it is, I
built this image, so
that's where those
are located at. And I
built Angban.
Remember, when we built
Angban, we got to tell
it where it's going
to be located. So I
built ArcBond with
the notion, hey,
this is the path that
you're going to find
your game data in.
It's all unique to this
repository image, right?
But I'm not in
the container. I'm
just seeing what
the file system
looks like for
the container,
all right?
If I control D out
of this, and so
I still got this
thing running here.
And so I can
do a control C
out of that
and kill that.
And now the
container is dead.
because when Ongban
stopped in the
container, the
container exits as well.
Make sense, everyone?
This is an example
running this.
So let's take a
look at a Docker
file. So here's a
Docker file I've
got in here.
Let's take a look
at what a Docker
file looks like.
So here's a Docker
file from a bug222
.04. This is how I
specify the base
image that I want
to build from.
I wanted one that
had a whole bunch of
typical Linux tools
in. So when I'm trying
to debug and figure
out why my container
is not working right,
I can always exec a
shell on my container
that's running and
go take a look at what's
going on. And I've
got some tools in
there. Now, one of the
tools that I would
like to be able to
use, like in OnBond,
if you run the strings
command on a binary,
it'll extract out
all the ASCII strings
in that binary file.
And so an easy way
for me to figure out
how Anban is built
specifically for where
it looks for its
game data, I can run
the strings command
against the Anban
binary and then type
that to a graph and
say search for game
data. And it'll pop
me out the string in
the binary file of
where it expects to
find the game data.
Except I couldn't do
that on this container
because strings,
while it's a great
tool, is not part
of the Ubuntu base.
and I didn't add
it to my OnBond
container when I
was building my
OnBond container
image, right?
So these are some
of the things.
So here I'm doing,
I'm building,
or basing this off of
Ubuntu version 22.04.
And here's where my
first layer is. My first
layer is going to have,
well, actually this
is my very first, this
is my base layer is
Ubuntu. Then I'm going
to generate another
layer on top of that,
which is an app get
update, which basically
says go update the
repository indexes to
the latest version of the
packages available
for Ubuntu. And then I
run another layer, run
app get install, and
I'm installing Python
in this because the
base Ubuntu does not
have Python 3 installed.
And then I run
another layer, which I
run install flask in
the thing. And then
I run hello.py, or
I copy my program,
this is my actual
program that I want to
run, I copy that hello
.py into the root.
Now, this is the one
thing that you've
got to understand
about Dockerfiles.
When you do something
like a copy,
the copy directive
in the Dockerfile,
what that means
is copy from the
build directory on
your host machine
into the Docker
image, okay? It's not
host file to host
file, and it's not
Dockerfile or Docker
image file to Docker
image file. It's
from the host machine
that you're building
from to the Docker
image that you're
building into. So it
says, hey, where I'm
building this from,
same place where my
Docker file is, I
should see a hello.py
file, and I want to
copy it into the root
of my Docker image.
And then finally I do
a couple things. I'm
going to go ahead and
set up an environment
variable that's
available to my process
when it runs. I'm
going to expose port
8000, which is a
way of telling the
Docker image to expect
to listen on port 8000,
that it expects this
process to be able
to consume information
from port 8000.
It has a volume, my
data, that it would like
to be able to map to.
And then this is how
it runs my program. It
says flask run minus
host and gives this
information for flask.
Flask, this is all about
running Flask to get
this done. This hello
.py is a Flask file.
So that's everything
in the Docker file.
So how would I use
this? So what I
would do is I would
do a Docker build and
then dot. What the
dot is actually is
just saying, where's
my Docker build
directory? I can run
Docker build from
anywhere and say,
this is the directory.
Oftentimes, we put
the Docker file in
the same location
where we're going to
build things that
we're already
building from. So
oftentimes, when we run
docker build, we
can specify dot. And
then wherever the
build directory is,
Docker will
automatically look for a
Docker file in that
build directory.
There is an
option, by the way,
on Docker build
to specify,
oh, here's my build
directory in my Docker
file, some other
location if you want to.
Now, when I run this,
this is where
it goes. And
this ran pretty quickly.
It went through and
built everything.
Okay, and so if we
take a look at this,
it says, okay, load,
build definition,
transfer, it's doing
some resolution stuff,
it says it's pulling
from the registry,
verifying the base Docker
image that I'm using,
internal stuff. and
then it says, okay,
it says we got all
that set up and then
say, okay, I'm going
to pull from the
base image. This is
layer one of five.
I'm going to run
app get update,
layer two of
five, run app get
install, run
the pip install,
copy the hello
.py. Each one of
those, there's five
different layers.
Now, notice this
word cache in front,
okay?
I have already built
this Docker image once.
And remember what
I was saying about
those layers? One
of the reasons
why we do the
layers so it can
automatically figure
out what's changed.
Nothing changed
in my Docker file.
So when I
rebuilt this, all
those layers came
out of the cache.
And so they actually
didn't do anything.
If I made a change to the
Docker file, actually,
here, let me do
this. I'm not going
to actually make
a change to the
Docker file. What
I'm going to do is
I'm just going to
touch hello.py.
This updates the
timestamp on hello.py.
Now watch me run
Docker build again.
Oh, it didn't work the
way it was supposed
to. This worked earlier
in the test. Well,
I'll do something even
more drastic. We're
going to say Docker
build dot no cache.
Now what it's going to do
is ignore all the layers.
I should have, when
I updated hello.py,
it should have not
cached that. It should
have grabbed a new
copy. It must have
done a check to
make sure that it
wasn't different.
This time, I'm saying
ignore all the layers
I've already built.
Now, this is going
to take a lot longer,
but it shows you
what's going on.
It's actually reporting
out as it's doing
the various build
operations. So right
now, we're doing an
app install Python.
It takes a little time to
install Python
on here, okay?
When I did this
before class, this
ran for about 40
seconds, this layer.
and we're done we got
through it a little
bit faster we got
time is at 25 seconds
to do this then we
installed blast that
went real quick and
then we installed
hello but i rebuilt
this and but this time
i built each layer
individually notice
the difference in
time when i was only
making one change only
had to build it one
way now if i had made
a change to layer
three say i added
additional package that
I wanted to install
aside from Python,
then layer three would
be, layer one and
two would be the
same, so it wouldn't
rebuild those, those
would we get in cache,
but if I added another
package for this
app install here, then
this layer would be
rebuilt, and then
every subsequent layer
would have had to
been rebuilt as well.
So this is just
getting you the basics,
I gave you a reference
to the Docker
tutorial to get started
on that i highly
recommend that you
guys go through that
practice a little
bit with this we're
going to take a look
at docker compose and
some other kinds of
things and also do
a little bit of
review for the midterm
on monday you guys
have a great weekend